avplayer.org
社区出品
Hey, Have you enjouy the week so far?
I am not sure if both my ears are working right, this half of room, have you enjoy CppCon so far?
you guys, what do you think?
I don't know they might have a next reduciable.
lets hear all of you one more time~~~
Thank you
This has been such an awsome week for c++ and also really feasible atmosphere here.
we want to thank you all very much for coming. and its been a blast.
we are now at our final plenary session
so I like to intruduce a speaker whose name happens to also be Herb.
Hi, my name is Herb.
You supose to say hi Herb.
It is been one year three months and 18 days since my last template metaprogram
Today I want to talk about the importance of resisting complexity.
I never thought it would happend to me.
I was intruduced to complexity by a friend, at least I thought he was a friend
He showed me a cool programming trick on his computer at home in private, and it really worked on his compiler.
So I started using a little complexity but just a little, not only at home
but after a while as I got used to using complexity, something strange happend to me.
the thrill sort of faded didn't seem as complex anymore
It seems simple - even no other people around me told me that was still too complex.
So I started hanging out with people after work for social complexity
on bar napkins.
but then I started eating at work time, we started bringing it into office,  checking it in.
some of you were at the template meta programming hacker fun last night. here's the picture
seriously the reason that I want to talk about complexity is
people under the influence of the complexity often think that they are thinking more loosely
and really that's not true.
but we get so used to complexity that we should remember that it's fine in moderation
once you know a lot about anything including c++ it's really hard to forget that you're an expert
so there's roughly give a take
it's hard to get a number
people who include use c++ on their daily jobs
is roughly around 3 millon for sometime.
and it's gradually little pretty flat in 2000s it's increasing a bit now.
but compare that to many of the experts that you've heard of
how many of you uses GNU GCC ?
lots! great!
so you're using the standrad implementation libstdc++
which has been around for quiet a while.
and just over the last almost 20 years, I ask some of the maintainers:
"you know, how many people have contributed to the well-know open-source project everybody knows that everybody contributes to opensource project? how many people really have contributed to it? say more than just a few lines, like contributed something significant to it?"
answer seam to be about 30 :(
gnu world in the last roughly 20 years
How many of you use clang?
if you're using XCode, that's also clang, so put up your hand
ok
you know how many people are developers of the standard c++ library that shipes with clang - libc++
the answer till 20 month ago is two.
they are both here at this week
one is now getting on a plane, the others still here in the audience
the answer is now about 5-7 that contributed more than just few lines
you contribute something more significant
I was not able to get the number of boost developers
that's been going on for almost 20 years now
I figure some where in the order of 300 people, maybe that's high, I don't know.
but must be generous
and ISO WG21 meeting attenders?
who like ever attended more than one c++ meeting, I didn't actually go through all minutes and count, but I'd be surpurized there's more than 300 people.
so here is a diagram
all the c++ developers in the world
and the smaller cycle is all of the libc++ developers, libstdc++ developers, boost developers, and anyone has attended more than one iso c++ meeting
and if I had put a border allying around the cycle you couldn't see the smaller cycle
actually I had to turn off the line around the cycle otherwise you couldn't see the smaller one
btw, can you see it?
we need to give good guidence to the big cycles.
while still teaching the advanced tools for people who need advanced code including very advanced code
but, a, not everyone need to know all of it
and not everyone who knows it needs to use it all the time
so that's the theme of this talk
in fact, if you go back to Bjarne Stroustrup's wonderful keynote on Tuesday
interesting factory
if you go through the slides, know how many "&&" presents rvalue references are in his entire talk
nice round number
so the value of simple usable defaults is really priceless
btw
I mention this some handle on monday night
the most important c++ book you should go out and buy it on bootstore now is a tour of c++ by Bjarne Stroustrup
we have lot... so much thunder so...
I know it was sold out! I know!
but the good news is that you can still order it on the book store and they will order and ship it to you, as they have free shipping
so go to the book store anyway or amazon or anywhere
in paticular
this book is important because it encapsulated in one place what every c++ programers should be expected to know
that's really important
somebody is coming new to c++ or they are learnning modern c++ after having knew c++98
they often ask, ok where? what's all the stuff we need to know
well, look over here on stackoverflow and Sculter got book bot and Stroustrup's stuff is longer, there's chapters there you ought to know
here is a 180 pages that some of you will have your time read on your plane home this weekend from cover to cover
that tells you the stuff that everyone needs to know about c++
I recomment this book
LET PEOPLE KNOW!
help get the world out
it's really important and I'm very glad that Bjarne has made that avaliable
in this talk I want to focus on
defaults, basic styles and idioms
now
some experts have push back me on this
when I say the word "default" some experts treated it as bad word
they say you are damping down the language, no, not.
a default does not damping down.
especially a default does not mean
"Oh~~ just do this blindly and donot think about it"
That's not what it is about
you should know your other options too.
but, a default is about
unless you have a good reasons to do something else (which does involve thinking) don't over thinking
Just do this unless you have reasons to do something more complex.
In paticular, this goes right in line with general good advice including these three idoms at the bottom of the screen which was the titles of 3 of the first 8/9 idoms in c++ coding standart not coincidentally.
write for clarity and correctness first
avoid premature optimization
in patirular, prefer clear code over optimal code
and that's almost a swear in c++ audience.
like, "we should be optimal by default". no you should not. you should have good performance by default.
and if anyone tries to tell you that C++ has been about writting optimal code by default
correct them gentally, because it has not.
c++ has always been about writting efficient code  not perfectly efficient or optimally efficient but good efficient code  by default.
and always been able to open the hood to take control
over memory layout, over the actual ... even down to the instructions (level) that get down  when you need to.
YOU DON'T ALWAYS NEED TO OPEN THE HOOD!
so, this talk is not about - don't think.
it's about, let's not over think
because it isn't a true we revel in complexity.
how many of you -- we're not gona put a camera on you, so non of your friends can tell you -- how many of you would say, ya, revel in complexity has discreeted me at least some point in my coding career.
I see all the speakers have their hands up, that's good.
so, this is good, we're acknowledging our problem then we can start to deal with it. we overcome denial, step one.
let's talk about range-for based loops.
you know, we can overthink range-for based loops.
I think that everything I want to say about range based for loops pretty much fits on one simple slide, and here it is.
WHY DO THIS WHEN YOU CAN DO THIS?
Any questions?
Now, some of you maybe saying, shouldn't I be writting "auto &&" there ? Maybe, but ...
wait-for, we'll talk more about "auto&&" at the end.
but, this is perfectly good, in fact, no matter whether "C" is a const or not, these code does the right thing because "auto&" also go through the iterators, if you get const iterator back that dereferenced to const T, it'll be deduced to the right thing so it'll be read-only for read-only collection. This is simple code!
if you are traversing every element of a collection, prefer to write range-for.
if you need early break, range-for does not support that yet. but the ranges proposal comming form the november meeting that I think will address that, even enable that.
Certenly if you're writting a for loop that reaches every element of the collection, just write range-for with auto& unless you want to modify in place.
soon, thanks to Stephan Lavavej, Stephan are you here? Wave if you're here. "喵～"
if I see one more solid coding examples checked in with kity, I will scream.
for ( e : c ) is going to be a short hand, that the standard commitee is seriously considering
and there are for some compilers once the commitee, will beless it hopefuly at the next meeting for c++17. are already start implementing it so you don't have to wait 3-years to start using this.
that basically sayes, you know what, we are gonna declare variable "e" for you and it will be of type  deduced what ever, so the constness will flow though.
and the nice thing about it, the first thing you might thinking is, how can c++ doing that? isn't that a breaking change?
haven't you suspect that the last line maybe a breaking change can change the meaning of existng c++14 code today?
Oh, you're scared.
I thought it was.  and then Stephan kept reminding me, "no, no. you can't actually write that today, you can't use existing variable you have to declare new one"
so we distract the type.
the default, the sensible default, will be essentially the same as before, auto && or auto&, which will do the right thing.
this desn't mean that you cann't lift the hood and write yourself if you want a certain type, or even write the naked iterator-based for loop if you want to do something more, like break, part-way thought or skip elements, that's all fine!
But defaults matter!
you are offen influences of people in your companies, of people who ask questions on stackoverflow, who participate in community.
so, please,  you teach starting from the bottom of the screen up, not the other way around.
now let's talk about smart pointers!
use smart pointers effectively!
But I still want you to use lots and lots and lots of raw pointers and references, they're great!
yeah, stern silence.
so, we hate pointers and references as raw pointers ... why do we recommend those? Those should be your default  parameter types and return types still! let's talk about that.
now, clearly, the code on the left hand side of the screen, was perfectly good code in books some time ago. but we tell people DON'T WRITE THAT ANY MORE!
in fact basically all the red stuff shouldn't pass  checking  anymore, in new code.
so, don't use owning pointers, don't use explicit new, don't use delete.
except, if you have real performance need and encapsulated down deep inside some low-level data structure maybe.
but FYI, I beleve even the entire STL can be implemented with no lost of performance using unique_ptr and no using new and delete.
we're about to try that!
and so
that "exception" might be even smaller than that you might think.
'cause unique_ptr is roughly free... is very thin overhead
often non at all over raw pointer.
modern c++ says: use unique_ptr, use a share_ptr, use make_unique
so, if you want to write new to allocate new object, use make_unique by default
if you know -- again, it's a default -- if you know this object is going to be shared, definitally use make_shared by default
if you don't know you are creating an object, hanging it out, you don't know it's gonna be shared stuff, use make_unique. cause you can always move that into shared_ptr
but if you know it's going to be shared, use make_shared
for delete, don't write anything
this is advice giving to people
how many of you follow that advice already in your codebase today? at least to your new code ?
looks like about half~~~ ok ~~~
how many of you try to follow this advice and found ... still found some dangling pointers problems with reference counted smart pointers ?
a few ! I have a slide for you!
I know the problem is, there is a cure.\
wait a few slides.
a very important qulifier on this: this slide says, don't use ownning raw pointers and references.
what does that mean?
really a pointer you should be calling delete on it at some point
Non-Owning pointers/references are awesome! keep writting them ! especially for parameters and return values
when you talk about structure lifetimes, where one function calls another funcion and that callee executes entirely within the scope of the caller because then you return/resume the caller, anything a calling function is keeping alive stay alive for as long as the caller function
now there is a reentrance case we'll talk about that.
but gentally this is nice as rushed all the way down where the lifetime nasted perfectly
you don't need owner ship transfer down the call stack.  \
unless you're gonna take something out of the call stack
you don't need to care about the owner ship
so in c++98 class we could say, hey if you need to look at the widget and say it's aquired parameter (ignoring const, we'll come to that later), pass by reference!
or, if it's optional, pass by pointer.
are you ready for the modern c++ advice ?
IT'S THE SAME !
it's the same advice
now if you have a unique_ptr, a shared_ptr, then you want to dereference it, or call ".get()" to pass & or *
but raw & and raw* for the win!
they still are the prefered parameter type.
think about this way, if you are not convinced about that, if you feel uncomfortable, think about this way:
unless you're talking about ownership transfering , in which case is perfectly valid to pass smart pointers, and I'll show that in just a second
unless the caller function is going to participate the ownership somehow.
if you just once look at the widget, why
why on earth as the callee care if they
why on earth does the callee care if you managing that lifetime by unique_ptr by shared_ptr by ... whether it's global whether it's global, he should be ignorant to that and this is how to write that.
very simple and the classic advice is still true.