avplayer.org
社区出品
好， 可以开始了
欢迎欢迎～看到那么多人我好兴奋啊～
特别是老朋友都在，还多了不少新朋友，我开心的紧张死了～
今天，我就来谈谈如何优美地写现代C++代码
我想大家和我一样，都被一个问题困惑，到底什么是好的现代c++代码呢？
过去的5年里，我们对c++做了不少手术
一些人开始觉得自己知道咋写好c++了
另外的人就开始追问了，“你知道？快告诉我啊”
于是今春，我决定开一个项目，告诉大家咋写好c++
于是发现其他人也有些个想法咯
于是我们来回答这个问题好了
且慢，谨记我们在帮助超过4百万的c++程序员
如果我们的办法仅有200个专家会用是没用的
所以这个项目的目的是要帮助更多的人
以及面前各位，现在我们有一个伟大的语言
这是一个现代语言，它能做10~20年前我们做不到的酷事
C++11非常酷，C++14更好。两者都在广泛的被使用中
这些都不是玩具语言
据我所了解的标准委员会正在制定的C++17使其更加完美
他们正在制定相关规范文件以及退出新的概念
因此，从我多年来的经验上认为，自从C++11之后将变得更容易实现、更容易维护、效率更高、阅读清晰、更精简
这是一个事实
实际上很少在做这样的事情
也许你认识一千人在写这样的现代C++代码
甚至你认识一万人正在写现代C++代码，但是他们始终还是很小的一部分
我们必须要做的更好
很多人在用SB的方式写C++
不信你去网上看，你会看到每个菜鸟都臆想自己是语音专家
和谈论各种右值引用的语法问题
这种问题存在于大多数代码中，除非你使用高性能库
所以他们都纠结在语言本身从而迷失在技术细节中
基本上的想法是："医生，用锤子砸我的头会伤害到我的".显而易见的答案是"不要这样做!"
而这正是我们想做的
这句话是我曾经说过的——
C++语言有较小的又安全的语言，要努力发扬光大
我想我当时说这句话的时候似乎是1994年还是1992年甚至更久之前了
今天看来依然正确
你可以简化代码你可以维持高效率，我们不限制你能说什么
这些都是重要的事情
这就是C Plus Plus！
它也不是专为特殊应用程序设计的语言
所以，让我们努力让它变得更好
很多人用它发明了更好更简单的新编程语言
但不是现在
如果你发明的新语言在十年内都有很多人在使用它，那么就算成功了
新的一般用途的编程语言能够成功收费盈利的可能性非常低
所以，让我们现在就做！
我想要使用这些编译器
我的意思是，你能使用你的编译器使你的代码优化多少？
doesn't matter which compiler you are using for a modern compiler and sort of standard hardware. 它是令人惊叹的。
我的意思是我不确定十年内能否完成它，但是他们这样做了很长时间
this doesn't just happen for a new language unless you can hijack the c++ code generation phase. which is a fair gain.
因此，我们需要去制定编码准则，为那些想写现代C++代码的人引路
并且，我应该告诉那些人什么事情不应该做
所以你需要工具和库的支持
而且我们想要程序通用、性能高、代码简单、程序轻简
我目前不想让C++程序运行在特殊的硬件和软件中
那些所有的捷不认输
我认为我们能够做到，我们不是孤军奋战
好吧，我知道确实有天才能办到
但是我想我可以确定一点，没有任何人可以做到
并且没有任何一家公司能够做到
它将让我们认识到某些公司的特殊兴趣
你完全不能相信这一切
很久以前我开始就参加了C++标准制定大会，所以请大家帮忙
我想要说一点关于能够帮助我们以及我们能够做到的事情
所以应该从最原始的工作开始
曾经有一个项目是来自于微软的Herb Sutter和他的朋友们
我开始的时候是在Morgan Stanley
欧洲核子研究中心（CERN）后来也加入，并作出了贡献
他们提交的那些代码都可用
他们的存在
你能够在github上找到它，给你们一个url
这里有一些准则，都在这上面
还有支持一些轻量级的库
那些大多是一些非常简答的类映射到标准库的东西，如果不直接映射到扩平台Ｃ＋＋
便携式的意义 Ｍicrosoft, gcc, clang; Windows, Linux
和mac.
这是一个分析工具，它是由微软的一个家伙写的
我们希望以后有可用的port，或许是十一月？我不知道，我的意思你们都明白软件项目时间易遭受延误。
but we are planning for it.
it exists. so I am saying anything in this talk that are science fictions.
and its MIT licensed, so its open and free.
so you can get it.
and there's more talk about this.
I am going to explain what we are trying to do with higher level terms with some examples
Herb Sutter is going to talk more about it.
Gabriel Dos Reis are going to talk how, er, ties into some of the work been done in the standard commitee for writting better code.
Neil Macintosh who wrote the tool that we work with, are going to talk about static analysis and some of the classes.
This is all this weak.
This is a problem with coding rules, with guide lines.
which is...
have you even seen one you really liked?
that might be necessary. but it's like medicine, doesn't taste good.
we all hate coding rules.
Usual caveats and thanks to the people who was made the less usual and paticular cases.
but basicly we don't like it.
and one of the reasons is that
coding guidelines tend to be written to prevent accident
so to keep novices that are not as smart as us from doing stupid things
so it's long lists of don't do this and don't do that.
and
I don't like such lists and I know most of you don't like neither.
and it's very often written at the start of an organization
when people is little bit uncertain about what they want to do and they want to avoid problems.
and rules tend to focus on low-level things
I mean, eh
do use camel case underscores
how many yea spaces to use to indent
these are all very interesting, could be in the essential for our organization
but it has nothing much to do with how you get quality software at the higher level.
how do you actually recognize a good piece of code when you came to see it?
a lot of them simply sets restrictions.
don't use overloading; don't use exceptions; don't use multiple-inheritance; don't use casts.... all kinds of rules like that
some are good. some are bad. some are good in some paticular environment. some are not.
And really, there is lot of bad advice out there.
there are guidelines that tell you that you really should trying write java.
when if you want to write java and you how to do which?
don't try to stop c++ programmer from writting good c++.
And "C with classes"? It was really cool in 1986
that a long time ago. a lot of you weren't born then.
and there are people think that really the world came to an end in 1978 when K&R came out.
and they might accept a few things they got from c++ like function prototype and const
but basically you really should write code as if we do it in C.
really dumb idea in my opinion, but we'll get to that.
also, coding rules get outdated.
I saw a recent year recommendation to use a  coding guideline , a really good guidelines, it describe how to write good code in about 198s. it hasn't been updated, that's a long time ago.
and so they became a drag.
a lot of code are specialized for particular application areas like I helped to write a set of guidelines for hard-realtime softwares or flight controlls
these are very nice guidelines for that.
but then people try use it in some other areas.
and you know, one of the guide rules for flight is that you don't use "new" after you take off.
and you never use "delete"
maybe these are not the most appropriate guidelines elsewhere.
other guidelines have similar kind of bias and constraint, and people tend to forget them.
and a lot of them are very long winded.
you really need to be a language lawyer to understand them.
I looked at the rules for how to use pointers in c++
I mean, I was miserable, I couldn't understand all those rules.
and you can't follow them, really.
and a lot of guidelines don't have very good tools
and they have platform dependencies
da
da~
and the don't produce guidance.
I really like to emphasize that telling people what not to do is less helpfull than telling what to do.
so let's do those good guidelines
comprehensive, browserable, for modern c++, for the moment
first of all, let's ignore legacy code, let's ignore old stuff. let's write the rules for what we would like our code to look like in 5 to 10 years
and then we'll deal with how to do the transition, how to do with  in compatibility when we have to.
gradual adaption is essential.
prescriptive teachable
one of the things that hold c++ back is that there are really a lot of bad teaching materials out there.
some of it is very old, some of it is backwards-looking
some of it try to maximize the pill by domain it down
and things like that.
so a setup guidelines can also guide teachers to how to teaching.
Flexiable of course. Because the huge community.
I mean
we recover just about everything that's been done on computing
And of course Non-proprietary.
We couldn't possibly do this with limits.
There are some high level rules and there are some low-level rules.
the high-level rules are there to provide a conceptual framework for everything
that sort of philosophical on nature.
and they are very useful.
like, you have to expre4ss ideas in code - compilers don't read the comments.
and you use ISO standard c++, yes there are reasons to use extensions as such
but we are not going to deal with that, that will be for paticular restrictions
And we want static type safety
etc.etc
so there a philosophical framework here
the problem is that again compilers and programmers don't really get philosophy.
it means that you have to transfer into something that can be understood in detail in context of a piece of program and use.
so for that reason there is a whole bunch of low-level rules.
that basically you guys should threw the massive alternatives and features
the low-level rules, things like, use T* to designate a single object, not array.
and prefer initialization to assignment in constructors
these are easily checkable.
we have a tool that tells you when you violate it.
Always initialize an object
compilers these days do. but it's a good rule and we can do even better with external tools that we have them.
so basically that sort of shows the way through the world dominance
and the tools provide feedback for programers, it also helps unify styles.
if I look at a piece of code and I see a string,
if I know it's std::string, I know a lot.
and it helped me, and I don't have to go back and read the manual again.
so a more unify style helps getting code written quickly, helps me read the code, understand the code
and one thing you should understand is that the rules and not mean to be minimal or orthogonal.
text book writters spend a lot of time trying to make sure that fix minimal amount of paper.
this is not we are up to
we try to have the most helpful, and have a large set tool to tell you when you fall over the edge.
so the structure of a rule is simple and structured.
"No naked new" for instance, it's a rule.
and Reference numbers - people love reference numbers
It also means that you can search for them.
I mean you can refer to them in error messages. things like that.
and NEVER NEVER tell people what not to do without giving a reason or what to do without giving a reason
so every rule with the first thing that comes up with the rule itself is that rational a reason.
and then it comes with an example.
because by and large we don't understand abstract text, we need a concrete example or more
if it's a "don't do this" rule, there should be alternatives.
never tell people what not to do unless you give them alternatives.
fairly simple to say.
little bit hard to do sometimes.
these rules are variable and value for a long time.
There's references to other things.
There's notes, things that we just felt was useful to say
and then, there suppose to be long discussion at the end where you discuss a set of rules, set of reasons as such.
it's bit weak just now.
but that's the idea.
some time you need more. as an explanation,  that what fits on above this many lines, fit right on your screen when you look at them.
so that's structure.
the general idea is that people who have tryed to subset language have by and large failed.
the thing that you really want to get rid of, like bad uses of pointers, bad interactions between inheritance and arrays and things like that
if you just ban everything to get rid of problems, you can't write decent code anymore
Yes! I want to write high-level code!
But how do I do that? I do that by having libraries that allow me to write high-level code, and they implemented it using low-level code.
because otherwise you can't get the efficiency and portability out of that.
So, the general idea is not just the subset.
First, we provide a superset.
we have ISO standard C++
we have parts of the standard library that we recommend and that's you can use when you want to.
and we have something called the guidelines support libraries which is small set - small as less than 2 dozen little classes and really that smaill - that's added.
And that way, we can say:
the messy dangerous bits, don't use them.
we have provided abstractions that are elegent and efficient to allow you to not go there most of the time, for most people, all of the time.
once you build that superset - the language + libraries.
the you subset, and you can get rid of a lot of the crack.
this is not a brand new idea I wrote a paper about it sometime more than ten years ago.
so, really what we want is not neutered subset of c++ which is a lot of people that tryed.
we want c++ on steroids on the other hand.
so more of a good stuff.
so the rules rely on the libraries.
you can use any standard libraries of course.
but once we rely on it, things like
standart library class like vector or unique_ptr
and some guideline things array_view -  this is when you have a begining of a sequence and end
not_null - you can say that a pointer shouldn't be null
now get back to that
so there's rules for using the GSL
Never transfer ownership by raw pointer
the idea is if you see a T*, it points to an element.
you are not suppose to delete it, because it just points to an element, somebody ownes it. that's it.
and if you want to have something that can not ever be null and you still want a pointer, you can use not_null of that pointer type.
now, there's rules that encourage you to use higher level abstractions
but these here are choose to show how you can deal with traditional old style code and improve it : don't pass an array as a ingle pointer.
so basically, guess what this could do'
I don't actually think that we can do less than can say double our productivity
this is big claim but I think it can be done
look at a good programmer working on a modern codebase and looking at same programmer working on a 20year old codebase or 10 year old codebase
also look at a median kind of programmer
and see what it taks to become a greate programmer.
you need support you need time
we can lower that time
so, I think we can imitate experienced programers form rule sets that we trying to enforce.
and so we can eliminate huge classes of errors.
so simplification is important
if we can have simpler code, maintance improves.
consistent style speed up learning
and guide people away from the deep dark corners of the law so much
so much programers spend so much of their time looking on the most complicated code and the most complicated rules of the standard
I'm shaking my head, I mean, this hurts!
why do you do it ?!
so I'm emphasis on avoiding waste, that can improve importance
My guess is every large organization/community that's doing this will need to have some special rules for what they are doing
so I'm talking about what I called the "core guidelines"
things that pretentiously help everybody
And I think most of you will want extensions in places.
and some of you will want restructuring tool because there is some one recommended us that it doesn't quite fit in your world or maybe doesn't fit there for the next couple of years till you upgrade your codebase.
and don't compromise performance
performance is a really important aspect
so I don't think I've gone mad
I think we are actually attacking what we known to be the common most serious sources of errors
and get rid of errors
no resource leaks! that's good, we know how to do that!
eliminate dangling pointer - that suppose to be very hard. I'll show you how to do that
eliminate out-of-range access - that can not be done without a few runtime checks
a few!! if you just check everything you are deracinate
but a few can be done and we have some suggestions about that
and Tool support is essential
a lot of this, humans are not very actually good at it
you look at a million lines of code and your eyes glares over.
you check for a paticular kind of error and mistake in a million lines of code, 100 lines of code 10000 lines of code
you get very tired and your concentration wavers.
we neeeed tools
the support library helps by simplify the rules
and a lot of it has to do is reinforcing the type system.
we can do better than we did it in 1978 and 1985
so let's look at the core, the core rules.
we have to start somewhere, so gradual adaption will be the way most of us will go on.
if we write some brand new code from scratch, not using anybody else's libraries. then you can probably follow all the rules today.
that doesn't happen very often.
so I see gradual adaption be necessary.
and therefore core of the core rules
No leaks, No dangling pointers, No type violations through pointers at all!
we know how to avoid leaks.
we just root every object in a scope
RAII kind of standard containers
new and delete disappear into the abstractions
this is nice. when I see "delete" in application code, there must be bugs somewhere.
why?
because if there is one delete, there probably should be more.
and there are probably been too many.
so new/delete disappear into classes
when you see a "new" in application code, you think there must be a problem here.
because if there's a new there should be a delete somewhere, and if there's delete somewhere and we know from experience we made mistakes.
so we don't do that.
this leads us to what I think is a worse nightmare problem.
dangling pointers
and this are so easy to get to.
here we have a function "f" that you give it a pointer and it deletes.
so you deleted that pointer.
that might be right or might be wrong.
my rulers on it, it's very suspect because it is deleting application code.
here is "g" makes an object, calls f.
and then it uses q which happens to be the pointing the the object that was deleted in f.
this is how you scram your memory
the rules will make sure that you don't do this.
and it'll take care of some of the most shroud and difficult find bugs
and we have to do this because if we don't we can damage type safety.
I say this object is an integer
you do this example
and the object might integer are laies at place where your object wasn't, you scramble it.
Memory safety of course.
because we are not using memory as if it is clear
and Resource safety is compromise because you can destory things that are laying around there.
double delete and no deletes
we have to solve this problem to get type safety to get resource safety.
we're going to eliminate this by combination of rules
I mean eliminated
get rid of it
we distinguish owners from non-owners
if I have a pointer, am I suppose to delete it or not? NO!
asure raw pointers to be non-owners!
we have many pointers in our programs, far too many, but let's asure they are all innocent, they just point to an object, they are not suppose to be a ownership
Catch all attempts for a pointer to "escape" into a scope that is outside a scope of what it points to.
fairly simple
anything that holds an owner is consider an owner
so all of this works recursively
so this is simple rule.
we have some pointers, they point to an object
that object is held alive by an owner
this works recursively
the object happens to have an owner pointer inside it
thus we have constructors and distructors. constructors to construct, distructors to clean up.
what we really have to avoid is that pointer there. that has been passed below the object owner in the stack so when we delete the owner the object is not there and people are still refering to it.
this must never happen so we can asure that. so long long way to eliminate (dangling) pointers.
this is not new rule
if you look at the standard it suggest you should not do that because it's undefined behavior
the point is how do we actully get there.
so here is dangling pointers thing again
first of all the rule will catch the delete p.
you had a innocent looking pointer X* that is not an owner. so the rules will tell you not to do that.
tools that enforce the rules will tell you that is bad
you go back to the "g"
it says, well, "new X" obviously produces an owner.
so assigning it to a plain old pointer is going to be wrong.
because this could lead to a leak
if fact it is also .. if do that will lead you to problems with exceptions, is another matter.
we'll never get down to the problem because you are already been traped by those simple rules twice.
so we can look at how we represent the ownership.
you can mark every owning pointer as owner
for a long time I think we need a bit to do that
that sort of dynamic module that took every pointer and mark it if owner or not.
I had modules like that before I put and saying whether it's a const or not , things like that
the point is it's useless!
It is very good for thinking about problems but it is useless for actually doing it
because, well, it cost time|space to have that extra bit, or time&space.
It means that the code that uses such smart pointers flat pointers as such are no longer ABI compatible with the existing code.
it runs slower than ordinary C or C++.
that's not acceptable
and we have to rewrite our own code for it
so the idea is that you just have a type system owner that static analysis tools can use.
when I talk about pointers I mean anything that can point to an object.
if we can handle it for pointers, we can handle it for everything, references, containers, smart pointers and things like that.
we are going to eliminate all dangling pointers.
oh yeah, down on the broader you can see the definition of an owner.
just as alien, we mark it as an owner
humans can read it, tools can read it
but your linker doesn't care.
so everything is working as before.
so here is how we can use it.
we can use an owner to improve our implementations of higher level abstractions, we want to use high level abstractions like vector and static array.
and we just mark that, in paticuler cases one of the 3 pointers inside the implementation of the vector is an ower and the other two aren't.
that's the owner, keep it alive, the others just pointing to it
that sort of the general you should see a lot.
and only if we are dealing with pointers directly do we use owners
so there's "f()" that taks an owner, and then trying to call it. I call it with an owner, that'll transfer ownership; I call it with non-owner,that's bad. I delete one of the owners, that's good; delete something that's not an owner, that't bad, we can catch.
and this is just marking, the static analysis tool will tell you when you did something that wasn't good.
an owner has to transfer to someone else or delete it.
the code will check whether you do it (or not) that's it.
and owners are low-leve mechanism.
you don't want to feddle with that all the time.
but having owner allows you to do two things
it provides the support for the implemention of high level abstrastions
it allows you to implement high level abstrastions
c++ are a language where you can design your own container, you can design your own smart pointers, etc
now you get a little bit support in how to express this.
and not make so many mistakes when you do it.
and further more as ABIs
somebody really says that they want any *, er, you don't have to give up all your checking to be able to use that ABI.
What else do we have to do?
we can handle owner ship now we have to handle dangling
Don't transfer to pointer to a local to where it could be accessed by a caller.
ok, let's look at the example there.
I am returning something.
I neither return a pointer to a local.
not a good idea, we all know that.
compiler are able to catch it more or less consistently for the last 20 years.
then I'm returnning a pointer to something I just created on the free-store.
that's fine.
at least it's sortof fine becauseIt didn't mark it as owner.
but as far as dangling pointers,it's not going to dangle.
and finnaly, there's a pointer that is given to me
then obviously I can give it back because it came from my caller.
those are roughly only 3 cases we can handle that.
we can stop pointers from escaping down to the bottom of the stack and out live the owner.
so catches all kinds of the things , pointers references etc and that's so fine
so, we need to classify acording to owner ship to work here.
because, look at the f() there.
it returns a vector of integers
and inside that vector of integers we put something that's an owner, something that's a pointer to a local and something we got from our caller
this... we can't handle the ownership, it just mixed.
that's bad code.
it's asking for touble.
it'll be rejected for mixing it.
in code we would have to try and deal with it and we can't
because clearly the ownership became mixed.
and when we passed it out, all the information about who shoud delete what has gone
the only way of doing that is actually to hav something like big vector of (what) that should tell you which should be deleted or you can sort of hope you can change into unique_ptr so that preseve the ownership.
don't mix ownership in containers!
bacause in corrent code it doesn't work too well.
in this code it'll be caught.
so let's course many other ways of mis-using pointers and such.
range errors, dereferencing nullptr
I'm going to go little bit about that
and I notice that there's a copy of printable here
some of the rules are meanable to static analysis.
some of them are meanable to sort of high G you can look at and give it as guidelines
and some of them really accquire runtime checks.
we want to minimize runtime checks because we want to run fast.
so here is one of the tools that we are providing - it's similar to the proposals in standard committee.
this one here, we'll do re-write, we have for some reason I don't understand at. the array view will be proposed in standard as read-only structure.
but anyway, here.
we have a common style
we call with a pointer and a count
this is my least favorite kind of interface
least favorite, because it is so error prone.
and least favorite because it is so common.
so a lot of errors there.
so I assign 9 to a[7].
it that ok?
we have no ways of knowing!
the information is not there
and I can make a loop,  let's hope a really was the count
and we hope the count was right, that's fine.
so instead, we provide you an abstraction that's array_view.
a begining that can browse integers, doesn't matter
there. you could check the runtime if you wanted to that a[7] is valid
and if you don't want the checks. we can only have it on debug mode
we can now write range-for loop that will work.
notice that there is not int n to get wrong and the code get simplified and is become more checkable
we are lifting the abstraction just a little bit.
and so we can look at some calls there.
I call it for a[100]
I have to say a and 100.
even though I have told there are 100 elements in a.
and if I finger flipson the keyborad and I write a 1000,  all kinds of bad things will happen
if it's a variable it gets more interesting
for array_view
well
you can just say it was an array_view or you can rely on the conversion  of an array to an array_view
it just socks on that array, makes it into array_view, having the size deduced
if you are going to call it on a value.
it's fairly easy to check agains the array of values there, if not you are on errors as often,
so this follows the idea of make simple things simple
and array_view is roughly the same as  (int*p,int n);
but we can use it easier and make few mistakes.
nullptr. deal with it simply by saying what we mean.
the problem is , today , we don't say what we mean.
I have f(char*)
is it alright to call it with nullptr ?
where does it say so?
in the documentation, OK.
compiler don't read document and neither do I  when I hear it
not a good thing.
when I implementing f().
should I turst my users (that they will) follow the rules or not?
should I test (against parameter)?
if I test, I test too much
because that's a waste of resources.
If I test too little, it'll crash.
there're all kinds of things about that.
so, one way to dealing with it is that we use not_null.
currently that's a class that will test whether it's null or not.
but a lot of it can be eliminated and can be debug only.
so if nullptr is an error it toke f(not_null<char*>)
and little bit saddle here. if you pass a variable that is not a pointer. that requires checking
but now we write f() we don't need to do the checking
so it's simplier and more class. it makes the code more explict, it detects a paticular specific well known problem.
thers's many ways to the tagging most problem this is the one way we choose for those.
so we go after bugs
we provide type and resource safety
now we can go after other problems
logic errors
performance bugs, maintenance hassles
there are rules going there.
but there are not as complete as things for extending the type-system.
one thing we noticed is that there is a lot of over use of smart pointers.
i noticed a lot of shared_ptr been used simply to return a value from a function
so the use count goes from zero to 1 and 1 to 2 and 2 to 1 and to 0
and all we did is to get something transferd simply because people didn't trust ordinary pointers
quiet resonably so because all ordinary pointers might dangle
wait a minite!
we just solved that problem!
so we have to re-think the way we're using smart pointers
shared_ptr in paticular
and my feeling is that they over used it.
a lot of protection in shared_ptr when used int that way is just a overhead.
because once the bugs have gone you don't have to have the use count anymore.
but it sits there forever counting what ever you called and passed a smart pointer
with smart pointers
with dangling pointers eliminated by tools you don't need to do that.
I'm going to show a little bit about it.
so here are the alternatives, in the standard we can take a T*
doesn't deal with ownership just a pointer
just use the pointer
with the rules here.
we know that f(T*) will not delete T.
the rules will stop that
it just point to something
if we want to transfer ownership we can use unique_ptr
if we really want to share ownership
we can use shared_ptr
but if we look at the T* it is familer, it's very general.
if I have shared_ptr, I can take the pointer out of it and give it to f();
I don't have to do anything fancy.
no dangling pointers
and think about pointers degenerate things and it works
so here is an example
if g() and h() has been written using different kinds of pointers
if I make it, f(shared_ptr<X>), if I make a shared_ptr<X> with make_shared<X>
then to call f(), I have to get the pointer
if I'm calling g(), we have the overhead of using pointers
and the h() I really have to modify. because if I pass the ownership in, I have to pass it out again unless I want it to be destoryed in h()
so we can keep things simpler now
simply use f(X*) as we always did.
one question I've had quiet resonably is would the rules be enforced by a compiler?
some could, some can't
on the other hand, I would like to use thiese rules now.
And I would like to use for all of the compilers
so, yes, it'll be nice if the compiler would use some of these rules
but
please be careful don't have false positives
people hate false positives
and that destoryes the whole system
because people does surprising things
and not worrying it
and further more
an external tool is not just useful accross the span of compilers
it also can tolerate a few more false positives
and it can handle changes more easily
you can use a compiler that enforce rules or the compiler are using false rules.
having an external tool helps
so let's start with an external tool.
and if the compiler writers get interested, that's so much better
and the other things
why didn't we just use the standard only?
because the standard currently as a stand doesn't have all the rules that we want for the standard for the GSL(the guideline library)
we want to use things now!
It's tiny, portable C++11
it doesn't depend on other libraries. free-standing.
you don't have to include whole broad of things you don't need.
it's a similar tool but not identical to boost:: and experimental:: components
that's actually good chance that it will become in some form or other.
but we are not going to wait
this is too simple
too easy, let's get going.
it's on github.
some of you've accessed yesterday or the day before.
and we use standard library
one of the things that you find with reasonably comprehensive or reasonably good old rules  set is that there's too many rules.
we need to help novices, experts, people with infrastructures, applicaions,
da
there are no way you can remember all of those rules
further more
I think I have 350 by now for this and no at the end.
these's too many and you won't even need to go and read them.
and, or,  more interstingly, you don't need all those rules
Most of you do it anyway, we don't make that mistakes
that we relearned that 10 years ago
so that all exist
every body knows it.
on the other hand
the rules are for the people that don't know it
the novices, the people that are casual users, people that has fifteen years experience on a different kind of code base. things like that, that's what the rules for.
and you can't sit wasting your time programming
trying to remember the rules or looking them up.
NO!
further more, you won't get there because the rules are extensible.
as we learned we add rules
so if last month you wrote something,
and you fulfill all the rules and this month you try again.
we hope to catch you again with some new rules.
that verified priciple, valided by experience will be helpful
and you shouldn't know all the rules, the tool knows the rules.
my idea is that you run the tool and it drop you right in there showing the rule on the screen.
what was the rule that violated?
where was it violated?
what's the rational for the rule?
what's the example of how bad it can get from problems like that?
and here is what you should do instead.
That's what I would like to see.
so thers is too many rules that doesn't worry me.
I want lots of rules.
here is a set of classification
there is philosophical rules
basically the conceptual framework
that cannot be validated
but it's really good if you understood what been said there.
if nothing else you'll know what we were thinking when we wrote them
and then there's all kinds of things, interfaces, functions, classes, class hierarchies
da
there's supporting sections, naming and layout
that's where every body goes and they say they don't like the rules we wrote that's fine.
never made anybody that the whole set of rules
people say that they want camel case.
sure, I hate camel case
apart from that.
what that c# camel case or java camel case ?
there's just too much of it
there's rules for performence.
some people interested in performence
there's different kinds of performence
some of these rules, you can go up and look at today now. but some of the areas are weak.
the guidence for standard library is weak
the standard for concurrency is fairly weak
because we hadn't have enough time
this as a project that infact started in April and we are shipping now.
This talk is trying to encourage you to help, to make it a community, a large community project
it is not some kind of polished academic things we'd like to
if we love to prove greate levels then this is the right thing
no, this is an attempt to do something major and something interesting.
this is not unambitious
we're trying to scale to the 4+ million c++ programmers and a few billion lines of code while not break the zero-overhead principle.
so the code will be better
no type errors, no resource leaks, no dangling pointers
da
we go after our least favorite bugs
so it's a full speed ahead, and we expect some rough waters
if you are thinking of a  sailing ship you can actually sail faster if there is a storm  going on
what's what we're headding into.
we actually aim to change the way we write code
and that means YOU.
what would you like your code to look like in 5 or 10 years?
and really honestly if the answer is just like what I wrote yesterday
there are some failling imagination here.
we really want to make change
that can be painful
it's not easy to modernize code, it's not easy to modernize a large codebase, it is painful
but, you know, if you don't do it. you have the same pain from your existing code
that now 10 years old code in 5 years will be 15 years old!]
and it is not going to feel any better!
and gradual adaption, of course is nessesary for this.
the idea of taking 5 million lines of codebase and saying, ok we just change this, and after the weekend we'll use the new version
hmmm...
probably not.
we will not agree what the code should look like so there'll be some discussions.
part of it will be, that not all code should look the same
I really don't want work under constraints from my flight control software when I'm writting ordinary applications, it just too painful
on the other hand there'll be discussion about what is common and what isn't.
if you look at the rules you'll find that some of them are some what controversial.
and that's fine.
I just choose what I'm presume right answer.
if you don't agree, I'll willing to argue with you.
so that's going to be fun!
and help wanted
look at the rules, help reviewing them
help man suggest new rules
help suggest better explanation of the rules
currently there's only two editors of this, me and Herb Sutter.
that is too lower number.
so we need more editors
but you have to earn your right to be an editor
that's a crucial positon in the community
so the current status, about 350 rules.
and there's a github for it
we put it live I think friday
and we already getting pull requests.
and thers's guidelines support library.
tested on clang, gcc, microsoft on windows, linux and mac
it's avaliable now
the first tool should come
microsoft is shipping something I think next month
I don't know their shipping schedules so it can't be percise.
and we hope ports to the other systems comming right after.
it's written as fairly intentive portable iso c++, so that should work.
and we need help
and
this paper, from my perspective means, that the basic c++ model is actually complete
hours going for the idea that you could get perfect resource safety and type safety now have been trying to get there for many many years, it was the idea from day 1 and I knew we couldn't get there in any time soon, I think we are there (now)
BTW
if you look at my definition of resource safety
you'll see that it's really not very many languages that can claim that.
and for static type safety, not very many languages can claim that.
no range errors and dereference errors without serious overhead, more language can cliam that but it's still hard.
this is not unambitious as I said
we now have concepts so we can deal templates in a more resonable way
so, with all of the problems solved from the resource point of view
why didn't I just go back to academia and design a new language?
That's after all what most people do right?
it's a cool thing to do
etc
competing wieh c++ is hard
I put these toolchains up there to show what anybody with a new languages are up against.
competing with c++ has over the years not been the winning strategy
and
it'll take, take time
and further more, certainly going into a new language could fracture the c++ community which is among the last thing I want to do.
so, we're going for something that can work now!
guidelines and tools, hope to get there.
so, with that, I'll switch to questions and I left the outline of the guidelines up there.
by the way
what we called guide there is Helios, Hercules fighting the Hydra.
this is a bit like what I feels like
we have many-headed monster we have to fight.
and there's a nasty tendency of getting more heads as we make progress
so, thank you!
～感谢 avplayer.org 制作英文字幕～
is there mic-phone somewhere?
OK, I am back. so the questions is "why do I mark the owner rather than non-owner?"
yes we discussed that
My conjecture is that there are too many hundreds of millions lines of code that uses T* to mean non-owner.
and I really don't want people to write very many owners.
I want the owers to disapper into abstractions
as for now, there are many more non-owners and owners
in the future, I expect there to be a thousand or more than a thousand times as many non-owners as owners in code
because pointers are now getting safer and you can use them more freely
so I think a got the owner/non-owner default correct.
maybe the first time in history of c++ we got default right. but I'm pretty sure this one is right!
Question here
there
Hi!
I had a question about owner T. and one thing I was confused about is that, is owner T is just something that is used at compile time or does it use any sort of like runtime overhead or ?
it's something that used only at compile time and it does absolutely nothing (at runtime)
it is something that guides or an enforcement tool to see what you suppose to do with it.
in paticular, if you're not an owner, you're not suppose to delete it
you're not going to pass it to an owner.
if you are an owner.
you have better either give it to somebody else who is also an owner or delete it
a tool can verify that, it doesn't do anything.
you can encapsulated an owner into a, say,  unique pointer.
and then just use it because it does the delete and has the right semantics
the owner is a low-level marker to help static analysis
I didn't mention but I sure static analysis is local, static analysis using very few rules, it's going to be fast
it's not one of these  going to be in cute algorithm over all of your code
it is local rules
What happens when you move from not null?
What happens when I move from not null?
into what?
you moved and the remaining status becomes null, right?
emmm
if you move from a pointer. it's just a copy. so it doesn't become null
if you generalized it to smart pointers and such
it will have to have the appropriate semantics, I don't know the implementations there, you should ask Neil Macintosh on Wednesday
he is one of the editor of the last version of the implementation which I haven't read yet
he made some improvements last week
but basically, no, you can not violate not_null that easy
I'm guessing
总结起来就一句话： do you have guidelines for makeing C api safer in c++?
I have no plans of dealing with foreign systems.
that will not be in the core guidelines
but I wouldn't be at all surprised and I'll be very happy if somebody would write a section asist how to interact with *, how to interact java, how to interact with python, I really hope to see somebody write those sections.
quiet likely they will be of the form that you can do this the static analysis to make it simpler
you can have this tiny tiny little setup classes for doing the transmission