avplayer.org
社区出品
Yes, Now we can go
Welcome~
It's very nice and a little bit scary to see you all again
And especially happy to see a lot of old friends and also a lot of people that are new here
Anyway, I'm going to talk about how to write code
and in particular
-- a question has been boggle for a while, and I know it has boggle for a lot of new people -- is
"What is good modern C++" ?
We've done lots to the the languages over the last five years
And lot of people have ideas about what it is to write good c++
and , lots of people ask about it.
so, this spring, I started a project trying to make some guidelines to how to write this
turned out that other people were on the same kind of idea.
so some of us try to provide some useful answer.
and one of the things that is important here, is that we would like to help many people
thers is more that 4million c++ programers.
and if we come up with a solution that can (only) be handled by 200 language experts, we failed.
so , this is an attempt to be able to help a lot of people.
and a lot of we've seen it, we have a great language now.
it's a modern language, it can do really nice things that we couldn't do 10-20 years ago.
c++11 is good. c++14 is better. both are in wide-spread production use.
These are not toy languages.
And from I see in the standards commitee, c++17 is even better.
There is technical specifications like filesystem and concepts and such that are rolling out. Things are happening.
So, I know from experience, from wide experience from industrial experience, that c++1* is easier to write, easier to maintain, runs faster and can express more that older c++ styles with less code
This is a fact
It's also a fact that very few people do it!
Maybe you know a thousand people that write such modern code.
Maybe you know 10 thousand people, but that's only very tiny small fraction of the community.
We have to do something better.
People are writting c++ in really archaic and foreign styles
Also you going to web and you'll see every little so-and-so trying to be language expert.
And discussing the sanitates of rvalue references.
Which does actually matter in most code unless you are writting a high performence library for use of others.
So, they are all trying to be language lawyers and getting lost in technical details.
so basicly idea is "Doctor, docker, it hurts when I hit myself on the head with a hammer". The obvious answer is "so don't do it!"
And that's what we are trying to do.
There is a quote by me --
Within c++ language there is a smaller simplier safer language struggling to get out.
I think I said that in 94, 92... It a long time ago.
it is even more true today that was there.
You can simplify the code
you can maintain the efficiency
and we don't limit what you can say.
these are important things.
This is C++!
It's not a so specialize language for a paticular application.
So, lets get it out! lets get it out now!
Lot of people solution to getting things better and simpler it to invent new languages.
but that not now.
If you invent a really good new language now,  large number of people will be able to use it, in 10 years, if you succeed.
The succee rate for new languages especially general purpose programming languages is very close to zero.
so, lets do it now!
And I want to use those compilers.
I mean, have you seen what compilers can do with your code interms of optimizing it?
doesn't matter which compiler you are using for a modern compiler and sort of standard hardware. it's amazing.
I mean, I am not sure what I could have done it if I had 10 years. but they did. this is going on for a long time.
this doesn't just happen for a new language unless you can hijack the c++ code generation phase. which is a fair gain.
So, I'm going to look for coding guidelines, provide guidence to people who wants to write modern c++ what ever that means.
And, I know that just telling people what to do doesn't quite work.
so you need support by tools and libraries.
and again, we want generality, we want performence, we want simple code, and we want portibility.
I dont want to be tight down by paticular hardware, paticular operation system.
those all the gameness.
I think we can do it. And I think we can do it, I know that I can't do it alone.
I know that well that might be a genius somewhere.
But I think I know that no individual can do it.
And, no single company can
It will be cature
and you couldn't trust it all time.
people explained that to me a long time ago to ensure that I took part in the (c++) standardization, so please help.
I'm going to say a little bit about what help we would like and who we are and things like that.
so the initial work started
there was a project out of microsoft by Herb Sutter and friends
I started something at Morgan Stanley
CERN has joined and contributed.
And things are available.
its there.
you can find it on github, give you the urls towards the end.
there is guide lines. a lot of them.
there is little support library.
which is some very simple classes that mostly mapping into standard library stuff if not  map straghtly into portable c++.
portable meaning microsoft, gcc, clang; Windows, Linux, Mac
and mac yeah.
there is analyze tool that will be ship by the guy at microsoft that wrote it next month
and we hope to have port available later. maybe November? I don't know. I mean, you know, software project some time suffer delays.
but we are planning for it.
it exists. so I am saying anything in this talk that are science fictions.
and its MIT licensed, so its open and free.
so you can get it.
and there's more talk about this.
I am going to explain what we are trying to do with higher level terms with some examples
Herb Sutter is going to talk more about it.
Gabriel Dos Reis are going to talk how, er, ties into some of the work been done in the standard commitee for writting better code.
Neil Macintosh who wrote the tool that we work with, are going to talk about static analysis and some of the classes.
This is all this weak.
This is a problem with coding rules, with guide lines.
which is...
have you even seen one you really liked?
that might be necessary. but it's like medicine, doesn't taste good.
we all hate coding rules.
Usual caveats and thanks to the people who was made the less usual and paticular cases.
but basicly we don't like it.
and one of the reasons is that
coding guidelines tend to be written to prevent accident
so to keep novices that are not as smart as us from doing stupid things
so it's long lists of don't do this and don't do that.
and
I don't like such lists and I know most of you don't like neither.
and it's very often written at the start of an organization
when people is little bit uncertain about what they want to do and they want to avoid problems.
and rules tend to focus on low-level things
I mean, eh
do use camel case underscores
how many yea spaces to use to indent
these are all very interesting, could be in the essential for our organization
but it has nothing much to do with how you get quality software at the higher level.
how do you actually recognize a good piece of code when you came to see it?
a lot of them simply sets restrictions.
don't use overloading; don't use exceptions; don't use multiple-inheritance; don't use casts.... all kinds of rules like that
some are good. some are bad. some are good in some paticular environment. some are not.
And really, there is lot of bad advice out there.
there are guidelines that tell you that you really should trying write java.
when if you want to write java and you how to do which?
don't try to stop c++ programmer from writting good c++.
And "C with classes"? It was really cool in 1986
that a long time ago. a lot of you weren't born then.
and there are people think that really the world came to an end in 1978 when K&R came out.
and they might accept a few things they got from c++ like function prototype and const
but basically you really should write code as if we do it in C.
really dumb idea in my opinion, but we'll get to that.
also, coding rules get outdated.
I saw a recent year recommendation to use a  coding guideline , a really good guidelines, it describe how to write good code in about 198s. it hasn't been updated, that's a long time ago.
and so they became a drag.
a lot of code are specialized for particular application areas like I helped to write a set of guidelines for hard-realtime softwares or flight controlls
these are very nice guidelines for that.
but then people try use it in some other areas.
and you know, one of the guide rules for flight is that you don't use "new" after you take off.
and you never use "delete"
maybe these are not the most appropriate guidelines elsewhere.
other guidelines have similar kind of bias and constraint, and people tend to forget them.
and a lot of them are very long winded.
you really need to be a language lawyer to understand them.
I looked at the rules for how to use pointers in c++
I mean, I was miserable, I couldn't understand all those rules.
and you can't follow them, really.
and a lot of guidelines don't have very good tools
and they have platform dependencies
da
da~
and the don't produce guidance.
I really like to emphasize that telling people what not to do is less helpfull than telling what to do.
so let's do those good guidelines
comprehensive, browserable, for modern c++, for the moment
first of all, let's ignore legacy code, let's ignore old stuff. let's write the rules for what we would like our code to look like in 5 to 10 years
and then we'll deal with how to do the transition, how to do with  in compatibility when we have to.
gradual adaption is essential.
prescriptive teachable
one of the things that hold c++ back is that there are really a lot of bad teaching materials out there.
some of it is very old, some of it is backwards-looking
some of it try to maximize the pill by domain it down
and things like that.
so a setup guidelines can also guide teachers to how to teaching.
Flexiable of course. Because the huge community.
I mean
we recover just about everything that's been done on computing
And of course Non-proprietary.
We couldn't possibly do this with limits.
There are some high level rules and there are some low-level rules.
the high-level rules are there to provide a conceptual framework for everything
that sort of philosophical on nature.
and they are very useful.
like, you have to expre4ss ideas in code - compilers don't read the comments.
and you use ISO standard c++, yes there are reasons to use extensions as such
but we are not going to deal with that, that will be for paticular restrictions
And we want static type safety
etc.etc
so there a philosophical framework here
the problem is that again compilers and programmers don't really get philosophy.
it means that you have to transfer into something that can be understood in detail in context of a piece of program and use.
so for that reason there is a whole bunch of low-level rules.
that basically you guys should threw the massive alternatives and features
the low-level rules, things like, use T* to designate a single object, not array.
and prefer initialization to assignment in constructors
these are easily checkable.
we have a tool that tells you when you violate it.
Always initialize an object
compilers these days do. but it's a good rule and we can do even better with external tools that we have them.
so basically that sort of shows the way through the world dominance
and the tools provide feedback for programers, it also helps unify styles.
if I look at a piece of code and I see a string,
if I know it's std::string, I know a lot.
and it helped me, and I don't have to go back and read the manual again.
so a more unify style helps getting code written quickly, helps me read the code, understand the code
and one thing you should understand is that the rules and not mean to be minimal or orthogonal.
text book writters spend a lot of time trying to make sure that fix minimal amount of paper.
this is not we are up to
we try to have the most helpful, and have a large set tool to tell you when you fall over the edge.
so the structure of a rule is simple and structured.
"No naked new" for instance, it's a rule.
and Reference numbers - people love reference numbers
It also means that you can search for them.
I mean you can refer to them in error messages. things like that.
and NEVER NEVER tell people what not to do without giving a reason or what to do without giving a reason
so every rule with the first thing that comes up with the rule itself is that rational a reason.
and then it comes with an example.
because by and large we don't understand abstract text, we need a concrete example or more
if it's a "don't do this" rule, there should be alternatives.
never tell people what not to do unless you give them alternatives.
fairly simple to say.
little bit hard to do sometimes.
these rules are variable and value for a long time.
There's references to other things.
There's notes, things that we just felt was useful to say
and then, there suppose to be long discussion at the end where you discuss a set of rules, set of reasons as such.
it's bit weak just now.
but that's the idea.
some time you need more. as an explanation,  that what fits on above this many lines, fit right on your screen when you look at them.
so that's structure.
the general idea is that people who have tryed to subset language have by and large failed.
the thing that you really want to get rid of, like bad uses of pointers, bad interactions between inheritance and arrays and things like that
if you just ban everything to get rid of problems, you can't write decent code anymore
Yes! I want to write high-level code!
But how do I do that? I do that by having libraries that allow me to write high-level code, and they implemented it using low-level code.
because otherwise you can't get the efficiency and portability out of that.
So, the general idea is not just the subset.
First, we provide a superset.
we have ISO standard C++
we have parts of the standard library that we recommend and that's you can use when you want to.
and we have something called the guidelines port libraries which is small set - small as less than 2 dozen little classes and really that smaill - that's added.
And that way, we can say:
the messy dangerous bits, don't use them.
we have provided abstractions that are elegent and efficient to allow you to not go there most of the time, for most people, all of the time.
once you build that superset - the language + libraries.
the you subset, and you can get rid of a lot of the crack.
this is not a brand new idea I wrote a paper about it sometime more than ten years ago.
so, really what we want is not neutered subset of c++ which is a lot of people that tryed.
we want c++ on steroids on the other hand.
so more of a good stuff.
so the rules rely on the libraries.
you can use any standard libraries of course.
but once we rely on it, things like
standart library class like vector or unique_ptr
and some guideline things array_view -  this is when you have a begining of a sequence and end
not_null - you can say that a pointer shouldn't be null
now get back to that
so there's rules for using the GSL